So back in our application, this is where we last left it, I'll add a new container. I'll add in the containers
Yani bavurumuzda, son braktmz yer buras, yeni bir konteynr ekleyeceim. Kapsayc klasrne ekleyeceim ve onu adlandracam.
folder and I'll name it auth,
Tabii ki
you can of course name this whatever you want
istediin hereyi yapabilirsin,
and there, I'll create the auth.js file and this will be this page I want to load with the sign up or sign in
ben de auth'u yaratacam. js dosyas ve bu sayfa ile kayt
form. Now in here, I will create a class based component
olmak veya kayt olmak istiyorum. imdi burada, snf tabanl bir
so I'll import react and component from react,
bileen oluturacam, bylece tepkiyi ve bileenin tepki vermesini salayacam, bu tr bir bileen oluturduumuzdan
it's been a time since we created such a component but I'm sure you still know how it works.
beri bir zaman geti ama eminim nasl altn hala biliyorsunuzdur.
We create it with the class keyword,
Bunu snf anahtar szc ile
then the name of the component like auth and we extend this component we're importing.
oluturuyoruz, daha sonra bileenlerin ad auth gibi ve biz ie aktardmz bu bileeni geniletiyoruz.
There we need a render method where we return some jsx and in the end, I'll export this class as
Orada bir jsx dndrdmz bir render yntemine ihtiyacmz var ve sonunda bu snf
the file default.
dosya varsaylan olarak vereceim.
Now the jsx here will be pretty close to our contact data form, I'll have a wrapping div and in
imdi jsx iletiim veri formumuza olduka yakn olacak, bir kaydrma div'um olacak ve
there, I'll add a form element and in this form element
orada bir form eleman ekleyeceim ve bu form
I want to use my custom input and button components, just as I use them in the contact data component
elemannda zel giri ve dme bileenlerini kullanmak istiyorum. Bunlar iletiim verileri bileeninde
or container.
veya kapsaycsnda kullanrm.
I'll also manage my form through the state of this auth container, not through redux because I'm only talking about
Ayrca formumu bu auth konteynerinin durumu araclyla da yneteceim, redux ile deil, nk sadece
the local state, the values the user entered into their form inputs and so on
yerel durumdan bahsediyorum, kullancnn form girdilerine girdii deerler vb.
and it makes more sense to me to use them and to manage them inside the container with react's state
Ve benim iin daha mantkl. onlar ve tepkinin devlet mlkiyeti ile konteynr
property.
iinde ynetmek.
So I'll add state here and I'll add a controls property and I'll set it up kind of equally to the contact
Bu yzden buraya eyalet ekleyeceim ve bir kontrol zellii ekleyeceim ve mantn iletiim
data so that I can reuse the logic from there,
verisine eit bir ekilde ayarlayacam, bylece
there we had an orderForm property and then we had the various controls and they all had something like
mant oradan yeniden kullanabilirim, orada bir orderForm zellii vard ve eitli kontroller ve
the element, type, config and so on.
hepsi eleman, yaz tipi, yaplandrma vb.
I'm going to copy the name control from there and put it into my auth controls object and rename it from
sim kontroln oradan kopyalayp, benim kontrollerimin nesnesine koyacam ve isminden e-postaya yeniden adlandracam,
name to e-mail,
imdi eleman tipi
now the element type will still be an input element,
hala bir giri eleman olacak,
the config here I will create an input element of type e-mail and placeholder should just be mail
burada konfigrasyon bir giri eleman oluturacam Tip e-posta ve yer tutucu sadece posta
address, for example.
adresi olmaldr, rnein.
Now the value initially is empty,
imdi balangta deer bo,
regarding the rules, I want to reuse the checkValidity method from contact data and there, I support
kurallarla ilgili olarak, ben checkValidity yntemini iletiim verilerinden tekrar kullanmak istiyorum ve orada, minLength,
things like required minLength, maxLength,
maxLength, isEmail, isNumeric gibi eyleri destekliyorum
isEmail, isNumeric and that is basically what I want to introduce in the auth container too.
ve temelde benim iin de auth konteynrnda tantmak istiyorum .
So I have required and now I also want to set up isEmail to true for this e-mail control I'm creating here,
Bu yzden gerekli ve imdi de oluturmak istiyorum bu e-posta kontrol iin true isEmail oluturmak,
valid initially should be false and touched is also false.
balangta yanl olmal ve dokunulduunda da yanltr.
And now, I will duplicate this once to also have a password field
Ve imdi, ben de bir parola alanna sahip olmak iin bunu
so here I'll add password like this, it will also be of type input
bir kez oaltacam, bu yzden bu ekilde parola ekleyeceim, ayn zamanda tip girdisi
but then, the element type will be of that, the type of the input itself then will be a password and the placeholder
olacak, ama sonra, eleman tipi o olacak, giriin kendisi o zaman olacak bir ifre olmal ve bu
will therefore be password.
nedenle yer tutucu ifre olacaktr.
It should be required
Gerekir ve diyelim
and let's say we want to have a minLength of seven characters or six characters
ki, yedi karakter veya alt karakterden oluan bir min uzunlua sahip olmak isteyebiliriz,
maybe, that actually is the minLength required by firebase, of course adjust this to your backend.
aslnda bu, firebase'in gerektirdii minLength, tabi ki bunu arka ucunuza gre ayarlayn.
With that we got this set up, we can now dynamically create that form and for that, I first of all
Bu kurulumu yaptk, imdi bu formu dinamik olarak oluturabiliriz ve bunun iin
need to import the input and button components
ncelikle girdi ve dme bileenlerini
so my own components there. Input from, now I need to move up into the components folder, into the UI folder
kendi bileenlerim oraya ithal etmem gerekiyor. u andan itibaren, bileenler klasrne, UI klasrne
then there the input folder with the input file and the same for the button component, like this.
gitmem gerekiyor, daha sonra girdi dosyas ile giri klasr ve bunun gibi dme bileeni iin ayn.
Now the logic is the same as in the contact data component,
imdi mantk, iletiim verileri bileenindekiyle ayndr, burada
there we also looped through all our controls here and I can therefore copy the code from there where
da tm kontrollerimizle burada da ilmikledik ve bu yzden kodu kopyalayabilirim ki, benim devlet nesnesini
I converted my state object to an array I can loop through, I'll copy that. I'll then move over to the
dnebildiim bir diziye dntrdm yerden kopyalayacam. . Daha sonra, auth konteynerine geeceim ve herhangi
auth container and add that in the render method before I return anything
bir ey dndrmeden nce bunu render yntemine ekleyeceim ve imdi
and now I want to loop through it and create my form. So I'll create a new constant which I'll name
bunun zerinden dnp formumu oluturmak istiyorum. Bu yzden ben form ad ve orada
form and there, I want to take my form elements array called map to map it into an array of jsx elements,
olacak yeni bir sabit oluturacam, jsx eleri bir dizi iine elemek iin harita ad verilen form eleri dizisi almak istiyorum,
I get each form element here and I will return jsx, I want to return my input,
ben burada her form eleman alyorum ve ben jsx dneceim, ben Giriimi geri vermek istiyorum, kendi kendine
it's a self-closing element and it takes a lot of keys and properties.
kapanma eleman ve ok fazla anahtar ve zellik gerektirir.
The first one is the key property,
Birincisi anahtar zellik,
there I really just want to use the form element ID which is available since I add it here.
burada gerekten sadece buraya eklediimden beri mevcut olan form esi kimliini kullanmak istiyorum.
If you remember the form's module, we added it here, it's the name of the element to be precise
Eer formun modln hatrlarsanz, onu buraya ekledik, enin ad tam olarak ve
and then, all the other keys which are expected. We can have a look at the contact data and we can actually
ardndan beklenen dier tm anahtarlar. letiim bilgilerine gz atabiliriz ve
copy all the set up from there, for all the other props
giri setine kurduumuz dier tm provalar iin
we set up on the input element and add it here in the auth container.
oradaki tm kurulumlar oradan kopyalayabiliriz ve onu auth konteynerine ekleyebiliriz.
So there we can also leave the code as it is
Bu yzden kodu da olduu gibi brakabiliriz nk
because I kept the name, I'm talking about a form element in my loop and I do use that here too.
ismi saklyorum, dngde bir form eleman hakknda konuuyorum ve bunu burada da kullanyorum.
I do have a config key and a value key and all these keys because I use the same set up in my state
Bir yaplandrma anahtarm ve bir deer anahtarm var ve tm bu anahtarlar benim
property so that's really reusable
devlet mlkmde ayn kurulumu kullanyorum, bu
and with that, we now have a dynamically generated set of inputs.
yzden gerekten yeniden kullanlabilir ve bununla birlikte, imdi dinamik olarak oluturulan bir girdi kmesine sahibiz.
Now the next thing is of course that I also need a button
imdi sradaki ey, elbette ki bu
so below all these inputs, I'll add a button. That button requires a button type prop which I'll set to
girilerin hepsinin altnda bir dmeye ihtiyacm var, bir dme ekleyeceim. Bu dme baars iin ayarlayacam bir dme tipi pervane
success, danger would be the other option we have in our application and that should not be part of my
gerektirir, bizim uygulamada sahip olduumuz dier bir tehlike de tehlike olurdu ve bu
form here though, that should be part of my form element down there where I return something and above
benim formumun bir paras olmamalyd, burada benim form elemanmn bir paras olmaldr.
the button, I'll render the form content which contains my inputs.
bir ey dndrmek ve dmenin stnde, girilerimi ieren form ieriini oluturacam.
With that, the button should not be a self-closing element but the button should allow me to add some
Bununla birlikte, dme kendiliinden kapanma eleman olmamaldr, ancak dme etiketlerin arasna bir balk eklememize izin vermelidir,
caption in between the tags,
bu yzden burada sadece gnderim yapalm
so here I'll simply say submit and now we got a form with inputs and a button. To see it,
ve imdi bir giri ve bir dme ile bir form aldk. Grmek iin, onu ynlendirme yoluyla yklemeliyiz, auth konteynerini
we need to load it via routing, we got the auth container and we set up all our routes in the app.js
aldk ve uygulamadaki tm rotalarmz kurduk. js dosyas.
So there I want to import my auth container, import auth from ./containers auth and auth again
Bu yzden, auth konteynerimi ie aktarmak istiyorum. / konteynerler auth ve auth tekrar ve
and now here, I'll simply replicate one of the routes and let's say for /auth, I want to load this
imdi burada, sadece rotalardan birini oaltacam ve / auth iin diyelim, bu
auth component, like that.
auth bileenini yklemek istiyorum.
Let's try this out and to be able to reach that,
Bunu deneyelim ve buna ulaabilmek iin,
I'll also go into my components folder and there to navigation, navigation items into the navigation
bileenlerim klasrne ve gezinme elerine, gezinme elerinin gezinme eleri bileenine gideceim, burada balantlarmz var ve ben yeni bir
items component,
tane ekleyeceim, ekleyeceim
here we got our links and I will add a new one,
/ auth iin bir balant ve
I will add a link to /auth and I'll give it a caption of authenticate, something like that. With that
ona bir kimlik dorulama yazs vereceim, byle bir ey. Bu kurulumla, uygulamaya geri dnelim,
set up, let's go back to the application, we are on
kimlik dorulamas yapyoruz, stil
authenticate, the styling is a bit off though
biraz kapal ve eer
and if we inspect it, I can't spot my inputs.
incelersek girdilerimi tespit edemiyorum.
So let's head back to the auth container and see where the inputs are at,
yleyse auth konteynrna geri dnelim ve girdilerin nerede olduunu grelim, bir
we have a form, that should be that form constant
formumuz var, bu formun sabit olmas gerekiyor
but somehow when looping through the array
ama bir ekilde dizinin
here, we seem to not really create inputs.
iinden geerken gerekten giri oluturmuyor gibi grnyor.
The reason is because I copied the code from contact data,
Bunun nedeni, kodun iletiim verilerinden kopyalanmas, benim
I'm referring to an orderForm property in my state but here in the auth container, I renamed this to controls
durumumdaki bir orderForm zelliine atfta bulunmam ancak burada auth konteynrnda bunu kontroller olarak yeniden adlandrdm,
so I'll just rename it here too
bylece buray yeniden adlandryorum
and now if we go back, we see the controls.
ve imdi geri dnersek kontrolleri gryoruz.
Now to also give this some styling, I'll add an auth.css file and I'll copy the styling from the contact
imdi de bu biraz stil vermek iin, bir auth ekleyeceim. css dosyas ve stilini iletiim verileri
data css file into there, replace the contact data class
css dosyasndan buraya kopyalayacam, iletiim snf snfn auth snfyla
here with the auth class and leave all the styling and in the auth.js file, I'll then import
deitirip tm stilleri ve auth'lar brakacam. js dosyas, daha sonra
my classes from the ./auth.css file and then I'll assign it to the wrapping div, so that the wrapping
snflarmdan ie aktarrm. / Kimlik dorulama. css dosyas ve daha sonra sarma divine
div here receives the class name which is classes.Auth, this newly added css class.
atayacam, bylece sarma divi snflar olan snf adn alacak. Auth, bu yeni eklenen css snf.
If we now save all these files,
imdi tm bu dosyalar
this is looking pretty good on all device sizes, I guess.
kaydedersek, bu tm cihaz boyutlarnda olduka iyi grnyor, sanrm.
So this is my sign up form, the next step is to also configure this form to have validation,
Bu benim kayt formum, bir sonraki adm da bu formun validasyona sahip olacak ekilde
so let's do that in the next step,
yaplandrlmasdr, yani bir sonraki
I will also copy the code for this from contact data
admda bunu yapalm, bunun iin de kod
and by the way with all these code copying, you would correctly say can't we outsource some of this code
verilerini iletiim bilgilerinden kopyalayacam. Doru bir ekilde bu kodun bazlarn merkezi bir dosyada
in some centralized file and yes we can,
d kaynak olarak kullanamayacamz ve
we'll do this in the next module where we will apply some optimizations to this project.
evet yapabiliriz, bunu bu projeye baz optimizasyonlar uygulayacamz bir sonraki modlde yapacaz.
For now, I would just wrap checkValidity, this method,
imdilik, sadece checkValidity, bu yntem, wrap kopyalayn
copy it and add it to my auth container too, so above render, I'll add checkValidity which supports various
ve benim auth konteyner iin de eklemek istiyorum, yukarda render, ben eitli kurallar, aslnda burada kullanmak
rules,
ve
actually all the rules I use here and now I need an inputChangedHandler and I will also get this from
imdi bir inputChangedHandler ihtiyacm olan tm kurallar destekleyen checkValidity ekleyeceim ve ben de bunu
contact data.
iletiim verilerinden alacam.
So to check the validity, I'll add a new method to my auth container, I'll name it inputChangedHandler
Bu yzden, geerlilii kontrol etmek iin, auth konteynerine yeni bir yntem ekleyeceim, inputChangedHandler olarak
and there, I expect to get the event and the control name which did change
adlandracam ve orada, olay ve deiimin yapld kontrol adn almay
and in there, I now can use a lot of the logic but not all from the contact data.
umuyorum, imdi ok kullanabiliyorum Mantktan deil, tm iletiim verilerinden.
I want to create an updated form, not named orderForm though where I update my elements but I'll
elerimi gncellediim yer olsa da gncellenmi bir form oluturmak istiyorum, orderForm deil ama
do it manually here in the auth container. So I'll create my updatedControls constant where I'll create
bunu elle auth konteynerinde el ile yapacam. Bu yzden, bunu kopyalayacam yeni bir nesne
a new object where I'll copy this.state.controls first and then I want to only update one of the
oluturacam gncellenmiControls sabitimi oluturacam. belirtmek, bildirmek. nce kontroller ve sonra sadece kontrollerden
controls, the control with the control name we have here.
birini gncellemek istiyorum, kontrol burada sahip olduumuz kontrol ad ile kontrol.
So state controls simply copies all elements inside this control object
Bylece, devlet kontrolleri bu kontrol nesnesinin iindeki tm elemanlar basite kopyalar ve bunlardan
and one of them will then be overwritten by me and that's the one with the name I receive as an argument
bir tanesinin zerine yazmam gerekir ve bu benim burada bir argman olarak
here and that should then in turn receive a new object.
aldm ve daha sonra yeni bir nesne almas gereken isimdir.
So here, I will then also call this.state.controls for that given control name and distribute all these
Bu yzden burada da diyeceim. belirtmek, bildirmek. kontrol adna verilen kontrolleri ve
properties so that I can then overwrite some of the properties,
tm bu zellikleri datn, bylece baz zelliklerin zerine
for example the value, now the value of this control and I can basically now overwrite all the properties
yazabilirim, rnein deer, imdi bu kontroln deeri ve temelde imdi burada kontrolmzdeki tm zelliklerin zerine
we have here on the control, like value and valid and touched.
yazabilirim. deeri ve geerli ve dokundu.
So the value will now be event.target.value, valid will use this checkValidity method and there I will pass
Yani imdi deer olay olacak. hedef. deer, geerli bu checkValidity yntemini kullanacaktr ve orada
event.target.value
olay geireceim. hedef. Bu
and the rules of this given control,
kontroln deeri ve kurallar,
so the rules are this.state.controls for this control name,
bu yzden kurallar budur. belirtmek, bildirmek. Bu kontrol ad iin
there we have this validation property which I'll pass,
kontroller, orada geeceimiz bu validasyon zelliine sahibiz, yani
so that is referring to that validation property each control has where I set up the rules.
bu kontrol zelliine atfta bulunarak her bir kontrol, kurallar belirlediim yere sahiptir.
So that is now what I pass as a second argument to check validity,
Bu yzden imdi geerlilii kontrol etmek iin ikinci bir argman
additionally, I'll add another property, touched, it will be set to true here whenever this inputChangedHandler
olarak geiyorum, ek olarak, baka bir zellik ekleyeceim, dokunduumda, bu inputChangedHandler her ne zaman ate ederse, burada doru
fires, the user did type something so it's definitely touched.
olarak ayarlanacak, kullanc bir ey yazd, bu yzden kesinlikle dokunuldu.
So with that, I update my individual control which was changed,
Bylece, deitirilen bireysel kontrolm gncelliyorum, deitirmek
I update all the relevant fields I want to change.
istediim tm alanlar gncelliyorum.
Now I deliberately won't handle the overall form validity here,
imdi kastl olarak genel form geerliliini ileyemem, bunu kontrol etmeyeceim,
I won't check this,
geersiz formlar
I won't disable the submit button for invalid forms because I also want to show what happens if we submit
iin gnder dmesini devre d brakmayacam nk geersiz formlar gnderirsek ne olacan
invalid forms,
gstermek istiyorum. Tabii
you can of course implement this too but I won't.
ki uygulayabilirsiniz. bu da ama yapmayacam.
So I'm pretty much done here, what I will have to do is I'll call set state in inputChangedHandler
Bu yzden burada iim bitti, ne yapmam gerekecek ben inputChangedHandler iinde
and set the controls property equal to my updatedControls
set durumunu arr ve updated zelliini imdi
now. With that, I got this working, now I need to connect it,
controlControls ile eit olarak ayarlar. Bununla alyorum, imdi balanmam gerekiyor, bunu
I already did this because I used the same name as in contact data,
zaten yaptm nk ayn ad, iletiim verilerinde kullandm,
so this should work.
bu yzden ie yarayacak.
Now let's save this and let's see if validation is working then, back in the project if I start typing
imdi bunu kaydedelim ve dorulama ileminin ie yarayp yaramadn grelim, burada yazmaya baladmda,
here, it stays invalid until it's a valid email address and the password has to be at least 6 characters
geerli bir e-posta adresi ve parola en az 6 karakter uzunluunda geerli olarak
long to be treated as valid.
kabul edilene kadar geersiz kalr.
So that's working
Yani bu
and as I said, the button is deliberately never changed.
alyor ve dediim gibi, dme kastl olarak hi deimedi.
So my form is finished,
Bu yzden formum bitti,
my next step is to now handle the submission and of course I want to do this using redux and action
bir sonraki adm imdi sunumu halletmek ve tabii ki bunu redux ve aksiyon yaratclarn kullanarak
creators.
yapmak istiyorum.